詹姆斯·韦布空间望远镜终于上天了 但要做的工作还有很多
The James Webb telescope is finally in space, but the work has not stopped there.
光学组件需要进行调整才能让我们看到宇宙遥远的过去
The optical instruments need to work for it to send us clear images of our distant past.
所有18块六边形镜面都要进行10纳米精度的调整
All the eighteen hexagonal mirror segments must align within ten nanometers of one another
才能组成一整块主镜
to form a single big primary mirror.
说说容易 做起来难
Of course, that sounds easier said than done
因为镜面调整所需的10纳米精度
because achieving this aim requires making fine adjustments
只有人类头发丝直径的万分之一
as small as 1/10,000th the width of a human hair.
这些调整阶段称为调相
The phase during which these adjustments take place is known as phasing.
镜面调整前后要耗时至少三个月
Remember that these adjustments can take at least three months to execute.
而这一切都完成后 望远镜的完全体就出来了
However, once the process is complete, the telescope will finally fulfill its function.
镜面调整流程一共分为七个阶段: 子镜面图像识别
The mirror alignment process includes seven phases: segment image identification,
子镜面调整 图像堆叠 粗调相 精调相
segment alignment, image stacking, coarse phasing, fine phasing,
基于仪器视场的望远镜调整 和基于仪器视场的迭代调整
telescope alignment over instrument fields of view,
and iterate alignment for final correction.
我们一起看看每个步骤的具体细节 来了解整个镜面调整的流程吧
Let's look at each of these phases in detail
to understand how the entire process will take place.
第一阶段需要调整望远镜与航天器整体的关系
The first phase requires the alignment of the telescope in relation to the spacecraft.
需要用到星敏感器引导航天器精确指向
It will use star trackers to make precise pointing moves,
而星敏感器对于航天器的作用就像GPS一样
as these star trackers work as a GPS for the spacecraft.
最开始 星敏感器引导航天器的方向和各个子镜的指向并不一致
Initially, the spacecraft position from the star tracker
will not match the mirror segment positions.
之后 望远镜会指向一个孤立的亮星(HD 84406)
Later on, the telescope is pointed towards an isolated and bright star (HD 84406)
捕捉到的图像被汇集到一起 拼一张星空的照片
to capture images that are brought together to form a picture of the sky.
当然 别忘了 拍摄星空的子镜不只有一块 而是18块
Of course, you must remember that there is not just one mirror looking at the sky
as there are eighteen mirrors,
每一块子镜最初都是各自为战 朝向星空的某一个点
each of which is tilted at the beginning towards a unique part of the sky.
因此 望远镜最后会得到18份目标恒星的照片
Because of this, the telescope will capture eighteen copies of the star,
每个都是失焦的 且有不同程度的失真
each one is out  of focus and has a unique distortion.
最初拍摄的这些目标恒星照片称为子镜图像
These initial star copies from the telescope are known as segment images.
根据每块子镜初始位置不同
Depending on the mirror's starting positions,
可能需要多次迭代才能确定每个图片对应哪块子镜
it might take many iterations to locate all the eighteen segments from a single image.
而NASA的工作就是要通过移动这些子镜
The job of the space agency
is to move the eighteen mirror segments to understand
来确定哪个图像对应哪个子镜
which segment creates which segment image.
当这些图像都找准谁是谁后
Once the matching of the segment is done to the image,
各子镜会把它们移动到对应其自身位置的点
the mirrors are tilted to bring all of the images near a common point.
这样可以进一步辅助图像的分析 这样排列后称为图像阵列
It helps analyze the image further, and such an arrangement is known as an image array.
镜面调整的第二步是子镜面调整
The second phase of mirror alignment is segment alignment,
这个过程可以修正子镜面的大部分定位误差
which is a process that corrects most of the positioning errors of the mirror segments.
该过程首先要轻微移动副镜 让子镜图像离焦
The process begins by defocusing the segment images
该过程首先要轻微移动副镜 让子镜图像散焦
by moving the secondary mirror slightly.
当然 离焦这一步骤并不容易 执行背后需要数学上的分析
Of course, defocusing is not easy and requires mathematical analysis to execute.
子镜面调整完成 相当于有了18个完成校准的望远镜
Once it is done, the segment adjustment leads to eighteen well-corrected telescopes.
但请记住 此步骤完成后 它们仍然是各自为战
Keep in mind that the segments are still not working as a single mirror during this phase.
接下来是第三步 图像堆叠
We move onto the third phase, which is known as image stacking.
这步中 我们要把所有子镜图像堆叠到一起 以便汇聚光线
During this phase, each segmented image must be stacked on top of one another
to put all the light in one place.
之后 每个子镜图像会单独调整
Then, the individual segment images are moved
让图像落在视场中心 形成统一的图像
so that they fall at the field's center to produce a unified image.
第三步可以为第四步的"粗调相"做准备
The third phase prepares the telescope for the fourth phase, which is Coarse Phasing.
对应子镜面编号A B C
并且图像堆叠会把子镜分为三组依次进行
The image stacking is one in a sequence in groups of three.
粗调相要把所有子镜面对齐
During the fourth phase, the segments must be in line with one another
误差要小于光的波长
with the precision and accuracy of something smaller than the wavelength of light.
粗调相本质就是测量并修正子镜面之间的垂直位移误差
Coarse Phasing is used to measure and correct
the vertical displacement of the mirror's segments.
这一步涉及到"色散条纹传感"技术
The technology used during this phase is called Dispersed Fringe Sensing,
18块子镜被分成10组 每组两块子镜
其中C2和C5镜面被同时分配给两组
所以是"10组 20块子镜"
子镜的标号可以看本视频2:13画面右侧
要用到近红外相机提取10组 20块子镜的光谱信号
and the NIRCam is used to capture light spectra
from twenty separate pairings of the mirror segments.
采集的光谱信号图样如视频所示
The spectrum will look like a barber pole pattern
译注: 平移误差越大 条纹越密集
平移误差的符号不同 条纹的倾斜方向相反
条纹的斜率与疏密可以反映出两块子镜之间的平移误差
with an angle or slope determined by the two segments and their piston difference.
译注: 粗->精->粗->精->粗->精
第四步的粗调相和第五步的精调相交替进行三次
The fifth phase, also known as Fine Phasing, is done three times after the fourth phase.
并且在望远镜的整个寿命周期内都要定期进行
Besides that, it will also be done routinely
from time to time during the lifespan of Webb.
这一步会使用离焦法修正之前调整后剩余的误差
The phase corrects the leftover alignment errors using the defocusing method.
不过这次不会再使用到副镜
However, the secondary mirror is not used during this phase.
而是使用科学仪器内部的特殊光学元件
Instead, special optical elements inside the instrument are used
为每个图像引入不同的离焦量
that introduce various defocusing amounts for each image.
下一步 基于仪器视场的望远镜调整
After this phase, it is time for the telescope alignment over instrument fields of view.
这一步中 调整会涉及到剩余的科学仪器
During this phase, the alignment will be extended to the remaining instruments.
多个科学仪器的多个视场点都会进行测量
The measurements are made at multiple field points across the various science instruments.
若某视场点的信号强度有明显差别 说明此处有较大的误差
The variation in intensity indicates that there are larger errors at that field point.
于是 人们会用一个算法计算最终需要的修正量
So, an algorithm will calculate the final corrections required
从而让望远镜上所有科学仪器都能达到完美校准的状态
to achieve the perfect telescope alignment across all the science instruments.
最后一步 为最终修正进行的迭代调整
Finally, we have the last phase, which is the iterate alignment for final correction.
这一步骤可以确保所有小的定位误差在主镜中得到纠正或消除
The final augment ensures that all small positioning errors
are corrected or removed in the primary mirror.
我们会使用第五步的精调相来进行测量与修正
The fine phasing process is used to measure and make any corrections.
之后会对每一个科学仪器的成像质量进行一次快速检查
After that, an image quality check is done across all the instruments,
如果质检通过 那么这一步就完成了
and once verification of the quality is done, the process is complete.
这七个步骤将确保望远镜主镜能被正确校准
These are the seven phases
that will ensure the proper alignment of the primary mirror of the telescope.
译注: 2022年2月25日 第三步图像堆叠已完成
此时 JWST团队已完成前三步
As of now, the Webb team has completed three phases out of the seven.
当然 这些步骤全部完成还要些时日
Of course, completing the phases will take time,
但完成后 我们就可以正式开始用它执行科学观测了
but once it is done, we will finally be in a position to start using the telescope for its purpose.
夏日来临之际
By the summer months,
JWST将会藉由其巨大的主镜传来第一张清晰的图像
Webb will finally send one of its clear images through this primary mirror.
希望JWST后续能一帆风顺 如履平地
Hopefully, everything will go as planned, and the telescope will not go through any hiccups.
期待镜面校准完成的那一天
We are excited to see where this goes and when the final mirror alignment takes place.
你们也期待吗?
Are you as excited as us?
欢迎在评论区唠嗑
Let us know in the comments below,
期待大家的反馈
as we would love to hear your thoughts on this entire process.
想看更多此类视频 欢迎关注
For more such videos, be sure to subscribe to our channel.